Okay, so in this lesson, we're going to be taking a look at Claude Code's plan mode, which is a read-only mode for creating implementation plans for new features, like the feature we expect in the previous lesson.
好的，在這堂課中，我們要來看看 Claude Code 的規劃模式（plan mode）， 這是一個唯讀模式，專門用來為新功能建立實作計畫， 就像我們在上一堂課規格化的那個功能。
Now, when we use plan mode to create a plan, Claude code spins up something called a sub-agent whose specialty is conducting research and gathering information about the code base and any additional context. And that sub-agent is responsible for providing that information back to Claude, the main agent, who then generates a plan markdown file, which is a robust set of instructions for implementing the plan, including code examples, file structure, styling guidelines, and so on.
當我們使用規劃模式建立計畫時，Claude Code 會啟動一個叫做子代理（sub-agent）的東西， 它的專長是研究並收集關於程式碼庫及任何額外上下文的資訊。 這個子代理負責將那些資訊回傳給 Claude 這個主代理， 主代理再生成一個計畫 markdown 檔案， 其中包含實作計畫的完整指令， 包括程式碼範例、檔案結構、樣式指南等等。
Then, once we have that plan, we can ask Claude Code to use it to implement whatever new feature it describes, and this added step of creating a plan is good, especially for multi-step complex features, because it allows for thorough research about how to best implement those features based on your current code base.
一旦有了計畫，我們就可以要求 Claude Code 用它來實作所描述的任何新功能。 加入建立計畫這個步驟是很好的，尤其對於多步驟的複雜功能， 因為它允許根據你目前的程式碼庫進行徹底的研究，找出最佳的實作方式。
And, as a result, you get a comprehensive guide about how to best add that feature to the project based on codebase analysis and not just guesswork. Also, having a plan document in place allows the model to refer back to it when it needs to, track its own progress as it's making the proposed code changes.
因此，你得到的是一份基於程式碼庫分析的完整指南， 說明如何以最佳方式將該功能加入專案，而不只是靠猜測。 此外，有了計畫文件，模型在需要時可以隨時回頭參考， 並在進行提議的程式碼變更時追蹤自己的進度。
And I find it better keeps things on track and produces more reliable working results. And finally, since we're making a plan document before any code changes are made, we can always manually refine that plan ourselves before we use it. So then, let's use this plan mode to make a new plan based on the spec we made in the last lesson.
我發現這樣能讓事情更有條不紊，並產出更可靠的結果。 最後，由於我們是在進行任何程式碼變更之前建立計畫文件， 我們隨時可以在使用之前自己手動調整那份計畫。 那麼，讓我們使用這個規劃模式，根據上一堂課建立的規格建立一個新計畫。
The first thing we need to do is enter plan mode, which we can do by hitting shift and tab to cycle through the auto accept edits mode and then again onto plan mode. And you can always tell you're in plan mode because it says so in green down here. But anyway, normally without a spec, you could send a generic prompt like, can you plan the authentication forms on the login and signup pages? And it would make a decent enough plan for that. However, we created a non-technical spec document to describe that feature so we can tell Claude to plan the feature outlined in that spec
首先我們需要進入規劃模式，方法是按下 Shift + Tab 來循環切換， 先經過自動接受編輯模式，再到規劃模式。 你隨時可以看出自己是否在規劃模式，因為下方會以綠色顯示。 不過，一般情況下沒有規格文件時，你可以傳送一個通用的提示， 例如「你能規劃登入和註冊頁面的身份驗證表單嗎？」 它也能為此做出一個不錯的計畫。 但是，我們已經建立了一份非技術性的規格文件來描述該功能， 所以我們可以告訴 Claude 規劃那份規格中概述的功能，
which contains much more detail about what we expect from the feature, more than just a couple of sentences directly in a prompt here. And this is why I make the spec file first, because it provides us with that high level but detailed outline of the feature, how it should work from a user's perspective and also edge cases to look out for, etc. So we're going to open that spec file now so that it automatically gets added as context to the prompt when we place our cursor inside it. And then I'll say down here,
其中包含了比直接在提示中寫幾句話多得多的細節， 說明我們對這個功能的期望。 這就是我為什麼要先建立規格檔案， 因為它提供了功能的高層次但詳細的概述—— 從使用者角度看功能應該如何運作，以及需要注意的邊緣情況等等。 所以我們現在要開啟那個規格檔案， 這樣當我們把游標放在裡面時，它就會自動作為上下文加入到提示中。 然後我在下面輸入，
plan the feature described in this spec. All right. And then once we've done that, we can hit enter. Now, when I do that, Claude code is going to go ahead and start running sub agents to explore the code base and perform some research. And I'm going to grant any permissions it needs along the way, which might occasionally be a bash command to list files or something. So I'll speed this up now and then I'm going to come back when it's finished.
「規劃這份規格中描述的功能。」好的。 然後這樣做完之後，我們就可以按下 Enter。 這樣做之後，Claude Code 會開始執行子代理來探索程式碼庫並進行一些研究。 過程中我會授予它所需的任何權限， 偶爾可能是用來列出檔案的 bash 指令之類的。 所以我現在要加速播放，等它完成後再回來。
Okay, so now it's finished. And if you scroll up this chat a little bit, it should give you a small summary of the plan, but probably not the whole thing. And that whole plan file was actually saved in the .claude folder in the home directory on your computer and not in this current project directory. It's also asking us at the bottom down here if we want to implement this plan now right away and allow edits whilst it does that. However, I don't like to implement anything right away.
好的，它已經完成了。 如果你在對話框中稍微往上捲動， 應該能看到計畫的簡短摘要，但可能不是全部。 完整的計畫檔案實際上儲存在你電腦主目錄的 .claude 資料夾裡， 而不是在目前的專案目錄中。 它也在下方詢問我們是否要立即實作這個計畫，並在過程中允許編輯。 但是，我不喜歡立刻就實作任何東西。
And instead, I like to look over the plan myself first and check everything is correct. And where it's not, I can manually make changes to it. So I'm going to key down to the bottom option down here and say, no, just save the plan to the underscore plans folder for later. I'm also aware we don't have an underscore plans folder anyway in this project. So before we send that response,
我喜歡先自己看過計畫，確認所有內容都正確。 如果有不正確的地方，我可以手動修改。 所以我要往下選到最底部的選項，說： 不，先把計畫儲存到 _plans 資料夾留著以後用。 我也知道這個專案裡目前根本沒有 _plans 資料夾。 所以在我們送出回應之前，
We need to go ahead and make that folder over here in the root directory. And actually, even if we didn't make this folder first, Claude code would probably figure it out and make it for us anyway. So then, now we can send the response and in turn, hopefully Claude is going to put that plan file inside the plans folder. Okay, so I think it's done that. And if we take a look at that file now, we can read through the plan. Now again, I'm not going to spend long on this because it's a long ass file.
我們需要在根目錄這裡建立那個資料夾。 其實，即使我們沒有先建立這個資料夾，Claude Code 也可能會自己想辦法幫我們建立。 那麼，現在我們可以送出回應， 希望 Claude 會將那個計畫檔案放進 plans 資料夾裡。 好的，我想它已經做到了。 如果我們現在看一下那個檔案，可以讀過整個計畫。 同樣地，我不打算花太長時間在這上面，因為那是一個超長的檔案。
And I'm quite aware that it would be really boring for you watching me read through all of this. So let's just quickly skim some of it. And normally, like I said before with the spec, I would spend longer going through this plan, 10, 15, sometimes 20 minutes, just making sure it's absolutely correct before we go any further. But anyway, we've got an overview at the top, which is to implement functional authentication forms for these pages, blah, blah, blah. So first of all, it's listed a bunch of critical files and new components that needs to create. So it's decided we want an input.
我很清楚讓你看著我把這全部唸一遍會很無聊，所以我們只是快速瀏覽一下。 通常，就像我之前說的規格一樣，我會在這份計畫上花更長的時間， 10 分鐘、15 分鐘、有時甚至 20 分鐘，確保在繼續之前一切都絕對正確。 無論如何，頂部有一個概述，是要為這些頁面實作功能性的身份驗證表單等等。 首先，它列出了一堆需要建立的關鍵檔案和新元件， 它決定我們需要一個 input（輸入）
component for text inputs along with the module CSS for that and the barrel export. Same for the password inputs. Same for a custom button down here. Then we're going to have a component for the login form. All right, so it's not creating the template directly inside the form itself, inside the page itself, I guess. It's creating a component for that, which I'm fine with. Same for the signup form. Additional pages to update. So you have the login and signup page. These are the updates we need to add to them.
文字輸入的元件，連同對應的 CSS 模組和 barrel export（桶狀匯出）。 密碼輸入也一樣。這裡還有一個自訂按鈕也一樣。 然後我們要有一個登入表單的元件。 好的，所以它不是直接在表單本身、也就是頁面本身裡建立範本， 而是為此建立一個元件，這樣我也沒意見。 註冊表單也一樣。 還有需要更新的額外頁面，就是登入和註冊頁面， 這些是我們需要對它們進行的更新。
Then test files to create, so we've got test files for each of these different components. Then we have the implementation step. So this is the plan itself, I guess. These are all the things it needs to create, and this is the plan. So step one, create the input components, and there's some details about how to do that right here.
然後是要建立的測試檔案，每個不同元件都有測試檔案。 接著是實作步驟，這就是計畫本身了。 這些是它需要建立的所有東西，這就是計畫。 所以步驟一，建立輸入元件，這裡有一些關於如何做到這一點的詳細說明。
And then down here, the styling approach, use apply for Tailwind utilities, reference theme variables for colours, style focus states with primary colour, add border and padding for input fields. Okay, all pretty good. Create password input component, pretty much the same as this one, I guess. And then icon usage. Okay, so it's showing how to use icons for the password field. So we've got I and I off, and they're coming from the icons package that we're currently using. Good. Same styling approach down here.
往下是樣式方法：使用 @apply 套用 Tailwind 工具類、 引用主題變數來設定顏色、用主要顏色設定聚焦狀態的樣式、 為輸入欄位加上邊框和內距。好的，都很不錯。 建立密碼輸入元件，大概跟這個差不多。 然後是圖示用法，它展示如何為密碼欄位使用圖示。 我們有 Eye 和 EyeOff，它們來自我們目前使用的圖示套件。很好。 下面的樣式方法也一樣。
And then we have the create button component. All right, looks okay. And then implementation, use type equals submit by default for the button, support disabled state with reduced opacity, keep existing hover transition from the button class. So it's where we've already created that button class. And like I said, this is what the plan mode is really good for. It's not just created this plan from scratch as if we've got a blank project. It's looked at our project first.
然後我們有建立按鈕元件的步驟。好的，看起來不錯。 然後是實作部分：按鈕預設使用 type="submit"、 支援帶有降低透明度的停用狀態、保留按鈕類別中現有的懸停過渡效果。 那是我們已經建立了 button class 的地方。 就像我說的，這就是規劃模式真正厲害的地方。 它不是從頭開始建立這份計畫，好像我們有一個空白專案一樣， 而是先看過我們的專案。
It's seen that we have this button class, it's seen that we've created components this way, where we've got three different files for each component. It's seen that we use this reference directive from Tailwind inside the CSS module, so it's explored the code base and it's based a plan on our current project, which is why this is so good.
它看到我們有這個 button class， 它看到我們以這種方式建立元件——每個元件有三個不同的檔案。 它看到我們在 CSS 模組裡使用 Tailwind 的 @reference 指令， 所以它探索了程式碼庫，並根據我們目前的專案制定計畫， 這就是為什麼這麼厲害。
All right, so down here we've got the create the login component step. So it's going to create the login form component with an email import, the password input component, the submit button component, et cetera. So it's creating all those UI components first of all, then it's kind of putting them all together in the login form. And it's got a code example here of how to create that using the input, the password input, and the button components. Then we've also got this link to switch to the sign up page instead.
好的，往下我們有建立登入元件的步驟。 它要建立帶有 email 匯入的登入表單元件、密碼輸入元件、提交按鈕元件等等。 所以它先建立所有那些 UI 元件，然後把它們組合在登入表單中。 這裡有一個程式碼範例，說明如何使用 input、password input 和 button 元件來建立它。 我們也有這個連結，用來切換到註冊頁面。
For the handler, we've got prevent the defaults form submission behavior, log e-mail and password to console, use controlled inputs with react states, some validation criteria here. And then the next step is to create the signup form component, same kind of things as the login one. And then we update the login page and the signup page to include those login components and the signup components. Then we create the tests down here to test everything and we've got
關於處理器，我們有：阻止預設的表單提交行為、 將電子郵件和密碼輸出到主控台、 使用 React state 的受控輸入，以及一些驗證標準。 然後下一步是建立註冊表單元件，跟登入那個差不多。 然後我們更新登入頁面和註冊頁面，加入那些登入元件和註冊元件。 接著我們在這裡建立測試來測試所有東西，我們有
Different guidelines for each of the different components, which is good. We've got some design decisions down here. All right, so component architecture is basically explaining why we're doing certain things, which is nice. So it said separate login form and sign up form components. So while they're similar, we're keeping them separate and that follows single responsibility principles and makes future divergence easier. So yeah, I would agree with that. Reusable input components, so input and password input can be reused across the app, again, I like that.
每個不同元件都有各自的測試指南，這很好。 往下有一些設計決策。 好的，元件架構基本上在說明我們為什麼要做某些事，這很棒。 它說要將登入表單和註冊表單元件分開， 雖然它們很相似，但我們保持分開， 這遵循了單一職責原則，也讓未來的分歧更容易處理。 嗯，我同意這一點。 可重用的輸入元件，input 和 password input 可以在整個應用程式中重用，同樣地，我喜歡這樣。
And then the button component, same as. A styling strategy. So yeah, just some things we've seen before. Form state management. We're going to be using new states. We've got a validation approach right here. And then navigation between forms. It's using the link components. Technical considerations. So we're creating TypeScript interfaces for the different props, like the input props right here. Accessibility.
按鈕元件也一樣。樣式策略——就是一些我們之前看過的東西。 表單狀態管理，我們會使用 state。 這裡有一個驗證方法。 然後是表單之間的導覽，它使用的是 Link 元件。 技術考量——我們為不同的 props 建立 TypeScript 介面， 例如這裡的 input props。無障礙性。
Yeah, aria labels, et cetera, icon integration, so the different icons we use. It's picked up as per the claude.md file that we don't wanna use semicolons, which is nice. Then we've got some verification steps as well. So you can do visual checks, functionality checks, bladder, bladder. So this is a really extensive plan. Okay, so I really like this feature. If I was just to use prompts in the chat of my own,
嗯，aria 標籤等等，圖示整合——就是我們使用的各種圖示。 它根據 claude.md 檔案抓到了我們不想使用分號的設定，這很棒。 我們也有一些驗證步驟，可以做視覺檢查、功能檢查等等。 這真的是一份非常詳盡的計畫。 好的，我真的很喜歡這個功能。 如果我只是在對話框中用自己的提示，
It wouldn't go to this length to make sure that this feature fitted correctly in our project and paired with the spec that we created, which was a kind of detailed high level specification. I think it's really powerful for adding new features. And this is the way I like to work. All right then my friends. So now we've done the first two steps, right? We have made a high level non-technical spec. And now we've also made a more detailed technical plan.
它不會費這麼大的功夫來確保這個功能正確地融入我們的專案， 也不會與我們建立的那份詳細高層次規格相配合。 我認為這對於新增功能來說非常強大，這也是我喜歡的工作方式。 好了，各位朋友。 現在我們已經完成前兩個步驟了，對吧？ 我們建立了一份高層次的非技術性規格， 現在我們也建立了一份更詳細的技術計畫。
Next, we just need to use this plan to implement the feature, which we'll do in the next lesson using extended thinking mode. But before we do that, I normally make a commit at this point to commit the new spec file and the plan file to the history. And that way, if the implementation doesn't go well, we can always rewind to this commit before we make any code changes and try again.
接下來，我們只需要使用這份計畫來實作功能， 這將在下一堂課中使用延伸思考模式來完成。 但在這之前，我通常會在這個時間點做一次提交， 將新的規格檔案和計畫檔案提交到歷史記錄中。 這樣的話，如果實作進行得不順利， 我們隨時可以回到這個提交，在進行任何程式碼變更之前重新嘗試。